Register of the Victor-Louis Chaigneau Papers, 1910-1954.
Hoover Institution Archives
Victor-Louis Chaigneau Papers,
1910-1954.
XX219
Chaigneau, V. L. (Victor Louis).
5 manuscript boxes (2.1 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Manuscripts of writings, memoranda, political campaign literature, and clippings, relating to social and economic legislation in France, particularly during the Vichy regime, and to French politics. Includes doctoral thesis of V.-L. Chaigneau, La Charte du Travail: Loi d'Octobre 1941.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Access Points
Industrial laws and legislation--France.; Labor movement--France.; Trade and professional associations--France.; World War, 1939-1945.; World War, 1939-1945--Collaborationists.; World War, 1939-1945--France.; France.; France--History--German occupation, 1940-1945.; France--Politics and government--20th century.
Series Description
- Speeches and Writings, 1924-1944. (Box No. 1-2.)
  Typewritten manuscripts of books, articles, essays and theses, arranged alphabetically by title.
- Subject File, 1913-1954. (Box No. 2-5.)
  Notes, studies and printed matter, arranged alphabetically by subject.
Container List
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1924-1944
  - L'Aspect moral du controle economique, 1944. Typescript and printed copy (Box 1.)
  - "Charite et revolution", 1924. Typescript
  - La Charte du travail, 1944.
    - Printed copy
    - Typescript, parts I and II
    - Typescript, part III (Box 2.)
    - Outlines and notes
  - "Le Christianisme et le temporel", n.d. Typescript
  - "L'Etat et le juste prix", n.d. Typescript of an outline for a book
  - "Les Finances du Ministere", n.d. Typescript
  - "Loi morale et vie economique", n.d. Typescript of the contents for a book which never materialized and of which all essays listed here (except for La Charte du travail and "L'Etat et le juste prix") would have been chapter headings
  - "Manifeste pour la revolution", n.d. Typescript of title only
  - "Ordre moral et technique financiere", n.d. Typescript
  - "La Richesse selon la Sainte Ecriture", n.d. Typescript
- SUBJECT FILE, 1913-1954
  - Albert I, King of Belgium (Box 2.)
  - American Express
  - Assyria
  - Australia
  - Bayard, Captain
  - Bernhardt, Sarah
  - Bonaparte, Louis-Napoleon
  - Book advertisements
  - Branly
  - Briand, Aristide
  - Comintern
  - De Valera, Eamon
  - Education, social problems of
  - Egypt
  - Europe
  - Foch, Marshal
  - Food, world scarcity of
  - France
    - Anarchism
    - Antisemitism
    - Bataville, Nov. 15, 1936 (weekly newspaper of the employees of Bata)
    - Civil defense
    - Colonialism
    - Communism
    - Economy (Box 3.)
      - General
      - Pre-Vichy period
      - Vichy period
      - Post-Vichy period
    - Family
    - Finance - 1943 and 1944 issues of the monthly newspaper, Finances Francaises
    - Legion
    - Literature
    - Pacifism - 1922, 1932 and 1933 issues of pacifist newspapers
    - Politics
      - General
      - Legislative elections
        - 1914
        - 1928
        - 1932
        - 1936
        - 1951
      - Parliamentary debates (Box 4.)
        - 1922
        - 1923
      - Vichy government
    - Prisoners of war
    - Religion
    - Rental legislation
    - Revolutions
    - Right-wing newspapers
    - Right-wing organizations
    - Royalism
    - Social legislation
      - General
      - La Charte du travail, the Law of October 4, 1940 (material used by Chaigneau for his thesis or relating to La Charte du travail, including a review of his work by Gaston Lecordier)
    - Socialism
    - La Vague, April 13, 1922 (weekly newspaper)
    - Veterans
    - Women
    - World War, 1939-1945
    - Youth
  - Geography
  - Germany
  - Great Britain
  - Greenland (Box 5.)
  - Habsburg, Otto von
  - Harmel, Leon
  - Health
  - Hitler, Adolf
  - Hungary
  - Imperialism
  - Indochina
  - Italy
  - Japan
  - Jaures, Jean
  - Jews, persecution of
  - Joffre, Marshal
  - Louis XIV
  - Maps
  - Marxism
  - Miscellaneous
  - Morocco
  - Munich Agreement, 1938
  - Natural science
  - New Commonwealth
  - Pasteur, Louis
  - Poincare, Raymond
  - Poland
  - Political economy
  - Psichari, Ernest
  - Racism
  - Rauschning, Hermann
  - Roditi & Sons
  - Roussel, Raymond
  - Sinclair, Upton
  - Social economy
  - Soviet Union
  - Spain
  - Stalin, Joseph
  - Switzerland
  - United Nations Charter
  - United States
  - Western resistance
  - World War, 1939-1945
  - Zaharoff, Sir Bazil